Inventory of the Erich Knapp papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Erich Knapp papers
1905-2005
2000C32
Hoover Institution Archives
116 manuscript boxes, 9 oversize boxes (58.4 linear feet)
Correspondence, writings, financial records, press releases, bulletins, newsletters, serial issues, clippings, other printed matter, and photographs, relating to West German foreign policy, political conditions in West Germany and reunified Germany, political aspects of Islam, and promotion of world peace through Islam.
Knapp, Erich.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2000.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
1932, April 13: Born, Heppenheim, Germany
1950-1952: Member of Bund Deutscher Jugend
1952: Graduated from high school
1954-1955: Attended University of Kansas on a Fullbright Scholarship
1955-1957: Studied political science, sociology, and history at Hamburg and Frankfurt Universities
1957-1958: Worked as a journalist at Frankfurter Neue Presse
1961-1963: Worked at IBM Deutschland in Sindelfingen
1963-1974: Served as Press Attaché in the West German Foreign Ministry (Auswärtiges Amt), posted at Bonn, Germany, and subsequently at N’Djamena, Chad; Lagos, Nigeria; Dhaka, Bangladesh; and Cairo, Egypt
1980-1981: Served on executive committee of the German Green Party (Die Grünen)
2006: Died
Scope and Content of Collection
This collection documents the political career of Erich Knapp through correspondence, writings, financial records, press releases, bulletins, newsletters, serial issues, clippings, other printed matter, and photographs, relating to West German foreign policy, political conditions in West Germany and reunified Germany, political aspects of Islam, and promotion of world peace through Islam.
The collection contains records primarily related to Die Grünen, the Sozialdemokratische Partei, the German Foreign Ministry (Auswärtiges Amt), as well as a number of other German political organizations. Another main focus of the collection is on Knapp’s advocacy of Muslim communities both in Germany and internationally. He belonged to several organizations that sought to promote religious tolerance and political equality for Muslims, including Tauhid Stiftung, Preussischer Nationalkongress, and Project Musa.
The collection is divided into twenty five series based on form and subject according to Knapp’s involvement in various organizations and political parties. The Correspondence series consists of Knapp’s personal and professional communications with individuals, government agencies, and religious organizations. The Printed Matter series consists primarily of newsletters, journals, magazines, pamphlets, and newspaper clippings related to German politics and culture as well as various religious themes. The Auswärtiges Amt series consists of correspondence and printed matter related to Knapp’s career in the German Foreign Ministry.
There are several series devoted to various members of Knapp’s immediate family, including his mother and father, Philipp Knapp and Luise Knapp respectively, and his wife, Ellen Knapp. A Biographical File consists of Knapp’s personal identification materials and newspaper clippings related to Heppenheim, Germany, Knapp’s place of birth.
The Writings series consists of drafts of essays and books on topics related to politics and religion, as well as handwritten notes on various subjects.
The Photographs and Negatives series consists of photographs, negatives, and photo albums containing images documenting Knapp’s family vacations and political activities.
A handful of series relate to Knapp’s involvement in various German political parties and organizations, including the Aktionprogramm der Sozialistischen Welteuropäischen Partei, the Bund Deutscher Jugend, the Christian Democratic Union of Germany/Christian Socialist Union of Bavaria, the Deutsche Gruppe der Liberalen Weltunion, Die Grünen, Reichsbanner Schwarz-Rot-Gold/Bund Aktiver Demokraten, and various groups advocating for Rheinland Independence.
Lastly a group of series document Knapp’s involvement with various religious organizations, including the Pressischer Nationalkongress, the Tauhid Stiftung, and Project Musa.
Whenever possible, the original folder titles given by the creator have been maintained. Within individual folders, materials have been kept in their original order as accumulated by the creator. Consequently, there is a great diversity in the forms of materials within individual folders; for example, correspondence files often contain newspaper clippings, pamphlets, or other items.
Bund Deutscher Jugend.; Freie Demokratische Partei.; Germany (West) Auswärtiges Amt.; Grünen (Political party); Sozialdemokratische Partei Deutschlands.; Germany (West)--Foreign relations.; Germany (West)--Politics and government.; Germany--Politics and government--1990-; Islam and world politics.; Journalists.; Peace.
- Luise Knapp File, 1905-1988
  Scope and Contents note
  Consists of correspondence, newspaper clippings, and personal identification documents related to Erich Knapp's mother, Luise Knapp (neé Hunold).
  - Correspondence, 1955-1975 (Box-folder 1:1-2)
  - Philipp Knapp funeral receipts, 1974 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Obituaries, 1982 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1988 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Identification documents, portraits, children's drawings, 1905, 1941, 1968, undated (Box-folder 1:6)
- Philipp Knapp File, 1905-1975
  Consists of correspondence, newspaper clippings, personal identification documents, and ephemera related to Knapp's father, Philipp Knapp, particulary to his fiftieth anniversary serving as director of the regional health insurance office.
  - Allgemeine Ortskrankenkasse correspondence, 1923-1963 (Box-folder 1:13-2:7)
  - Congratulatory correspondence, 1964 (Box-folder 2:10-3:2)
  - General correspondence, 1923-1954 (Box-folder 1:10-12)
  - Identification documents, portraits, children's drawings, 1905, 1941, 1968, undated (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1953-1973 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - School notebook, undated (Box-folder 121:4)
  - Passports, 1927, 1953, 1973 (Box-folder 1:7-9)
  - Work anniversary certificates, 1954, 1964 (Map case, Box-folder 2:8-9; 121:1)
- Ellen Knapp File, 2001
  Consists of the personal correspondence of Ellen Knapp (neé Rösgen), Knapp's wife.
  - Congratulatory correspondence, undated (Box-folder 3:3)
  - General correspondence, 2001 (Box-folder 3:4)
- Biographical File, 1931-1998
  Consists of personal idenfication documents and other personal items, as well as correpondence, newspaper clippings, and various printed materials related to Heppenheim, Germany, Knapp's place of birth.
  - Children's drawings, 1967 (Box-folder 120:1-2; 121:4)
  - Wallet, drawings, 1952, undated (Box-folder 3:8)
  - Home architectural plans, 1960 (Map-case case)
  - Horoscopes, 1995, undated (Box-folder 3:9)
  - Identification card, 1966 (Box-folder 3:10)
  - Datebook, 1974 (Box-folder 3:11)
  - Passport, 1992 (Box-folder 3:12)
  - Heppenheim File, 1931-1981
    - Correspondence, 1992-1997 (Box-folder 49:3-5)
    - Informational pamphlets, emphera, 1931-1966 (Box-folder 4:1-4)
    - Newspaper clippings, children's drawings, 1974-1998, undated (Box-folder 4:5; 48:6-49:2)
- Photographs and Negatives, 1919-1981
  Consists of family photographs and vacation photographs taken at various locations including Spain, France, Portugal, Morocco, and Switzerland. This series also contains a commemorative collection of photographs documenting the 1936 Olympic Games that took place in Berlin.
  - Various vacations and family, 1919-1981 (Box-folder 4:6-8:12, Box 119, Box-folder 122-127)
  - 1936 Olympics commemorative photograph collection, undated (Box-folder 8:13-15)
  - Oversized photograph of unkown German town, undated (Box-folder 121:2)
- Correspondence, 1947-2005
  Consists of both personal and professional correspondence with political and religious organizations, government offices, and individuals. Correspondence has been kept in original order as designated by the creator, who at times grouped correspondence together based on subject matter, sender, or format. This series contains four subseries of General correspondence that were arranged alphabetically by the creator according to subject matter or the name of the individual or organization with whom Knapp corresponded.
  - African matters, 1991 (Box-folder 55:4)
  - Al-Monsour, Khalid Abdullah Tariq, 1991-1998 (Box-folder 55:8)
  - Baha'i matters, 1985-1988 (Box-folder 84:8)
  - Berufsverbot, 1974-1980 (Box-folder 50:1-4)
  - Bonhoeffer, Walter, 1977 (Box-folder 91:1)
  - Bund Freier Bürger, 1994-1997 (Box-folder 56:3)
  - Bundesrepublik Deutschland lawsuit correspondence, 1976-1980, 1999-2004 (Box-folder 111:5-112:2)
  - Bürgerpartei, 1979 (Box-folder 48:2-4)
  - Congratulatory, 1956-1962, undated (Box-folder 74:1-5)
  - Conrad Ahlers controversy, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 61:5-6)
  - Czechoslovakia, 1972 (Box-folder 91:12)
  - Deutschland Konfrenz, 1994 (Box-folder 56:4)
  - Deutschland Stiftung, 1984 (Box-folder 71:1-2)
  - Frankfurter Neue Presse, 1953-1959 (Box-folder 31:5)
  - Free International University, 1972, 1976-1978 (Box-folder 41:1-2)
  - Freiheitsbund, 1960-1973 (Box-folder 40:3)
  - Friedenspolitik, 1980-1982 (Box-folder 47:6-8)
  - From Erich Knapp to Ellen Knapp, 1957-1964 (Box-folder 3:5-7; 33:1-2; 102:3-103:7)
  - Gauck-Behörde, 1993-2001 (Box-folder 97:9-98:1)
    Consists of correspondence relating to Knapp's request for access to personal files collected by the former East German secret police, the Stasi. The federal agency tasked with maintaining the files after the reunification of Germany was officially called Der Bundesbeauftragte für die Stasi-Unterlagen, but was often informally refered to by the name of the incumbent commissioner of the office, who at the time was Joachim Gauck.
  - General correspondence, 1947-2005 (Box-folder 22:4-25:10; 92:5)
  - General correspondence, alphabetical, I, 1956-1972
    - A-D (Box-folder 19:1)
    - E-K (Box-folder 19:2)
    - L-R (Box-folder 19:3)
    - S (Box-folder 19:4)
    - S-Sch (Box-folder 19:5)
    - St-Z (Box-folder 19:6)
  - General correspondence, alphabetical, II, 1953-1970
    - A-B (Box-folder 19:7)
    - C-G (Box-folder 19:8)
    - H-J (Box-folder 20:1)
    - J (Box-folder 20:2)
    - K (Box-folder 20:3-4)
    - L-M (Box-folder 20:5)
    - N-S (Box-folder 20:6)
    - S-St (Box-folder 20:7)
    - T-Z (Box-folder 20:8)
  - General correspondence, alphabetical, III, 1968-1973
    - A-B (Box-folder 21:1)
    - C-J (Box-folder 21:2)
    - K-L (Box-folder 21:3)
    - M-Sch (Box-folder 21:4)
    - St-Z (Box-folder 21:5)
  - General correspondence, alphabetical, VI, 1969-1982
    - A-E (Box-folder 21:6)
    - G-H (Box-folder 21:7)
    - I-J (Box-folder 21:8)
    - K (Box-folder 22:1)
    - L-S (Box-folder 22:2)
    - Sch-Z (Box-folder 22:3)
  - Gesellschaft für Musikalische Aufführungs, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 109:7)
  - Giordano, Ralph, 1988-1992 (Box-folder 97:5)
  - Havemann, Robert, 1977 (Box-folder 40:7)
  - Horst Lummert defamation lawsuit, 1997-2002 (Box-folder 94:5-97:2)
  - International Atomic Energy Agency, 1966 (Box-folder 40:6)
  - Iranian Embassy invitation, 1996 (Box-folder 40:8)
  - Islamic matters, 1997-1999 (Box-folder 56:2; 104:5-108:1)
  - Keitel, Ulrich, 1955-1970 (Box-folder 113:4-6)
  - Kluthe, H.A., 1963-1967 (Box-folder 40:9)
  - Knapp Family, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 34:7-35:1; 71:4)
  - Landessozialgericht, 1961 (Box-folder 33:3)
  - Letters of condolence for Luise Knapp's death, 1982 (Box-folder 47:4-5)
  - Lüling, Günter, 1977, 1989-1992 (Box-folder 90:6)
  - Lummert, Horst, 1981-2004 (Box-folder 98:3-101:2)
  - Nazis in the Freie Demokratische Partei, 1962-1964 (Box-folder 74:7)
  - Pfaff, Ivan, 1971-1971 (Box-folder 91:10)
  - Philosophical matters, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 86:3)
  - Postcards, 1958-1987 (Box-folder 41:3-5)
  - Publishing, 2002-2003 (Box-folder 94:1-4)
  - Rheinischer Merkur, 1953-1969 (Box-folder 33:9)
  - Schliesen, 1992 (Box-folder 43:1)
  - "Der Spiegel" and "Stern,", 1964-1965 (Box-folder 40:10)
  - Sudetenland Germans, 1971 (Box-folder 91:11)
  - Unemployment, 1974-1980 (Box-folder 71:3)
  - Unternehmansgruppe Tengelmann, 1991-1994 (Box-folder 101:5-6)
  - Walkoff, Karl Heinz, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 91:1)
  - Weizsäcker, Carl Friedrich von, 1977 (Box-folder 91:7)
  - Worch, Christian, 1997-1998 (Box-folder 9:1)
- Printed Matter, 1915-2005
  Consists primarily of German political, cultural, and religious publications.
  - Commemorative postcard collections, undated
    - "Deutsches Leben in 5 Jahrhunderten,", undated (Box-folder 32:6)
    - "Raubstaat England,", undated (Box-folder 32:7)
    - "Gestalten der Weltgeschichte,", undated (Box-folder 32:8)
    - Heppenheim, undated (Box-folder 32:9)
  - Die Aktion, 1983 (Box-folder 9:2)
  - Aktuell, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 26:5-27:2)
  - Am Zeitstrand, 1997-1998 (Box-folder 110:1)
  - Anti-Semitism and Emotional Disorder, 1950 (Box-folder 115:5)
  - Art reproduction collections, 1967, undated (Box-folder 120:4)
  - Auf dem Wege nach Weimar und von Weimar nach Potsdam, undated (Box-folder 112:6)
  - Bonn Koblenzer Strasse, 1967 (Box-folder 113:1)
  - Bonner Extra-Dienst, 1982 (Box-folder 121:6)
  - Bonns Graue Eminenzen, 1970 (Box-folder 117:2)
  - Die Brücke, 1965-1969 (Box-folder 34:5)
  - Bundesrepublik Deutschland reports, 1960-1968 (Box-folder 84:9-10)
  - Bundestag election results, 1969 (Box-folder 117:3)
  - Bundesverfassungsgericht, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 114:2)
  - Centurio, 1993 (Box-folder 92:4)
  - Christian Democratic Union posters, 1981 (Box-folder 62:4)
  - Collection of essays on communism, 1962 (Box-folder 58:5)
  - Collection of etchings of Königsberg, undated (Box-folder 122: 3)
  - Constitutions of various countries, 1919-1946, undated (Box-folder 14:1)
  - "Contre l'Europe germano-americaine et l'election d'un parliament et son service,", 1975 (Box-folder 33:7)
  - Demokratische Partei Saar newspaper clippings, 1959-1980 (Box-folder 40:1-2)
  - "Dem Deutschen Volk: Der Reichstag in der deutschen Geschichte,", undated (Box-folder 114:1)
  - Der Deutsche Rhein, photograph collection, 1968 (Box-folder 122: 2)
  - Deutsche Studentenzeitung, 1953 (Box-folder 97:3-4)
  - Die Deutschland Stiftung e.V., 1978 (Box-folder 116:5)
  - Diplomaten ohne Nimbus!, 1970 (Box-folder 113:2)
  - "Du und die Seele deines Kindes,", 1929 (Box-folder 112:7)
  - Environmental pamphlets, 1983-1991 (Box-folder 55:5)
  - Der Ewige Bund, newsletter and related correspondence, 2000-2002 (Box-folder 101:9-102:2)
  - Exhibition program and related newspaper clippings, 1964, undated (Box-folder 117:5)
  - Die Fehlwege Deutscher Geschichte, with related correspondence, 1966, undated (Box-folder 112:3)
  - French archaeological guide, 1986 (Box-folder 62:1)
  - Führer durch das braune Bonn, 1969 (Box-folder 47:1)
  - "Fünf Tage im Schwarzwald,", undated (Box-folder 41:8)
  - Für die Freiheit eine Gasse, 2003 (Box-folder 118: 3)
  - German commemorative historical magazine, circa 1950s (Box-folder 120:6)
  - German cultural pamphlets, 1987-1990 (Box-folder 118:1)
  - German press correspondent member directories, 1988 (Box-folder 50:7)
  - German and French leftist political writings and related correspondence, 1977-1981 (Box-folder 60:5-61:4)
  - "Die Glocke,", 1915-1917 (Box-folder 10:2-3)
  - Greek book illustrations, undated (Box-folder 56:8)
  - Gustav Heinemann commemorative magazine, undated (Box-folder 35:3)
  - Gustav Heinemann Iran trip controversy and related correspondence, 1971 (Box-folder 91:13)
  - Haben die deutschen Diplomaten versagt, 1959 (Box-folder 47:2)
  - "Höchst am Main," reproduction of drawing, undated (Box-folder 120:3)
  - Jammu Kashmir Liberation Front pamphlets, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 56:1)
  - Internet printouts related to the Taliban, 2001 (Box-folder 33:8)
  - Der Islam und die Bestimmung des Menschen, photocopy of book, 1987 (Box-folder 93:7-8)
  - Kämpfende Kunst, 1977 (Box-folder 122: 1)
  - Der Katastrophenweg der Deutsche Geschichte, 1947 (Box-folder 112:4)
  - Konservativ!, 1953 (Box-folder 112:5)
  - König der Welt, photocopy of book, 1956 (Box-folder 41:9)
  - Kriegsweinacht, songbook, 1941 (Box-folder 92:3)
  - Die Krisis der Neuzeit, photocopy of book, undated (Box-folder 101:4)
  - Kuckuck, and related correspondence, 1979-2001 (Box-folder 37:1-39:6; 56:5-7; 97:6-8; 110:3-111:3)
  - Linker Extradienst, 1982-1983 (Box-folder 32:10)
  - Links Europa, 1982-1983 (Box-folder 108:5)
  - Libya reports and related correspondence, 1986-1989 (Box-folder 55:6)
  - Martin Walser and Ignatz Bubnis newspaper clippings, 1998-1999 (Box-folder 41:10)
  - Mitteilungen,with related correspondence, 1968-1974 (Box-folder 71:5-6)
  - Die Morgendämmerung, 1986-1989 (Box-folder 14: 10)
  - Der Morgenstern, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 9:3-7)
  - Muckensturm, 1953 (Box-folder 118: 4)
  - Nazi commemorative magazine, undated (Box-folder 50:5)
  - "Nazis in Bonn's Service,", 1974-1975 (Box-folder 90:7)
  - Neue Politik, 1980-1985 (Box-folder 58:7-59:3)
  - Neue Solidarität, 1988-1993 (Box-folder 86:4-5)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1944-1998 (Box-folder 32:5; 34:4; 40:4-5; 58:6; 91:8; 114:3; 116:3-4)
  - Nigerian popular culture magazine, 1968 (Box-folder 35:2)
  - Nigerian newspaper clippings, 1967 (Box-folder 71:9; 74:6)
  - Nouveaux Philosophes newspaper clippings, 1977 (Box-folder 91:6)
  - Das Ostpreussenblatt, 1992 (Box-folder 84:7)
  - Oversized German magazines, 1953, undated (Box-folder 120:5)
  - Portugal: Wege und Irrwege, with related correspondence, 1978-1979, undated (Box-folder 50:6)
  - Der Primat der Innenpolitik, 1965 (Box-folder 50:6)
  - Prophets of Deceit, 1949 (Box-folder 115:6)
  - Publishing pamphlets and related correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 116:2)
  - Qimosh, 2000 (Box-folder 110:2)
  - Rheinischer Merkur, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 33:10)
  - Ritualmord als Grundlage/Urdogmas des Christentums und seine Folgen, manuscript, undated (Box-folder 47:3)
  - Sehr geehrter Parteifreund..., 2001 (Box-folder 117:1)
  - "Shamsallah,", circa 2002 (Box-folder 98:2)
  - "Shirdi und Shamsallah,", undated (Box-folder 101:3)
  - Sleipnir, 1995-1998 (Box-folder 14:8-9)
  - Socialist pamphlets, books, and newsletters, 1973-1976 (Box-folder 55:9-10; 62:3)
  - South African Muslim newsletters, 1990 (Box-folder 61:7)
  - Spiegel Spezial: Die Globale Revolution, 1991 (Box-folder 58:4)
  - Studien von Zeitfragen, 1982-1991 (Box-folder 108:2-4)
  - Styleskji, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 104:4)
  - Swiss anti-census newsletters, 1981 (Box-folder 62:2)
  - Unger Varnsdorf Nacherzählungen, 2000 (Box-folder 111:4)
  - Various religious pamphlets, newsletters and magazines, 1922, 1986-2005 (Box-folder 9:8; 32:2-3; 41:7; 55:7; 108:6-109:1)
  - Various German political journals, newsletters, and pamphlets, 1915-1999 (Box-folder 10:4-13:3; 32:2-3; 33:11-34:3; 117:6-7; 118:2)
  - Vertrauliche Briefe der Gesellschaft zum Studium der Zeitfragen, 1953-1957 (Box-folder 82:1-3)
  - "Weltkarte des Idrisi," map, undated (Box-folder 121:3)
  - West German economic pamphlet, 1977 (Box-folder 59:5)
  - Wir Selbst: Zeitschrift für Nationale Identität, 1980-1981 (Box-folder 55:2-3)
  - Die Zeit, 1969 (Box-folder 117:4)
- Aktionprogramm der Sozialistischen Westeuropäischen Partei File, 1975-1976
  - Correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 85:6-86:1)
  - "Zur Südeuropa - und 3 - Welt - Politik der SPD," essay, undated (Box-folder 86:2)
- Auswärtiges Amt file, 1961-1996
  Consists of correspondence and printed matter related to Knapp's various postings as press attaché for the West Germany Foreign Ministry. This series also contains correspondence, court documents, press releases, and newspaper clippings related to Knapp's dismissal from the Foreign Ministry, an episode dubbed by the German press as the "Knapp Affair."
  - Lagos, Nigeria, 1963-1968
    - Correspondence, 1963-1968 (Box-folder 62:7-63:5)
    - Household inventories, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 62:6)
  - N'Djamena, Chad, 1963-1966
    - Correspondence, 1963-1966 (Box-folder 63:6-7)
  - Cairo, Egypt, 1967-1979
    - Correspondence, 1967-1979 (Box-folder 64:5-6; 67:3-6; 72:4-73:1)
  - "Knapp Affair,", 1960-1996
    - Correspondence, 1960-1996 (Box-folder 64:7-66:4; 68:2-4; 88:1-90:5)
    - Court documents, 1975-1978 (Box-folder 68:5-69:1)
    - Press releases and newspaper clippings, 1975-1979 (Box-folder 66:5; 72:3)
  - Printed matter, 1961-1966
    - "Das Auswärtige Amt," pamphlet, 1966 (Box-folder 66:6)
    - "Visit to Cameroon of the President of the Federal Republic of Germany and Madame Luebke," programs, 1965-1966 (Box-folder 66:7-8; 73:2-3)
    - General pamphlets and reports, 1962-1966, undated (Box-folder 66:9-67:1)
    - "Runderlasssamlung für Pressreferent,", 1961-1963 (Box-folder 73:4-6)
  - General correspondence, 1961-1983 (Box-folder 64:1-4)
  - Foreign travel documents, 1969 (Box-folder 67:2)
- Bund Deutscher Jugend file, 1950-1986
  Consisting of correspondence and printed matter related to the Bund Deutshcer Jugend, and political organization of which Knapp was a member.
  - Printed Matter, 1950-1957
    - Newspaper clippings, 1952, 1957 (Box-folder 13:4)
    - "Informationdienst," newsletter, 1950-1952 (Box-folder 13:5-6)
    - Press releases, 1951-1952 (Box-folder 32:1)
  - Correspondence, 1951-1986 (Box-folder 13:7-9; 71:7-8)
- Bundes Presse Amt file, 1967-1974
  - Departmental documents, 1971-1974 (Box-folder 57:6-7)
  - Correspondence, 1967-1974 (Box-folder 58:1-3)
- Christian Democratic Union of Germany/Christian Socialist Union of Bavaria file, 1970-1977
  - "Quellen und Zitaten," report, circa 1970s (Box-folder 85:1-3)
  - "Verhinderete Staatpartei," book, 1974 (Box-folder 85:4)
  - "Weissbuch," report, 1977 (Box-folder 85:5)
- Deutsche Gesellschaft für Weltfrieden und Ökologie durch Weltföderation file, 1985-1991
  Consists of correspondence and handwritten notes related to the Deutsche Gesellschaft für Weltfrieden und Ökologie durch Weltföderation, an organization founded by Knapp to promote world peace through Islam.
  - Blank stationary, undated (Box-folder 70:9)
  - Correspondence, 1987-1990 (Box-folder 69:5-70:8)
  - Notes, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 69:2-4)
- Deutsche Gruppe der Liberalen Weltunion file, 1959-1976
  Consists of correspondence and printed matter related to the Deutsche Gruppe der Liberalen Weltunion, a political organization of which Knapp was a member.
  - Correspondence, 1959-1976 (Box-folder 59:6-60:4)
- Tauhid Stiftung file, 1988-1997
  Consists of correspondence related to Tauhid Stiftung, an organization founded by Knapp to promote world peace through Islam.
  - "Tauhid oder Schirk," essay, 1994 (Box-folder 14:2)
  - Correspondence, 1988-1997 (Box-folder 14:3-7; 101:7)
- Die Grünen file, 1966-1985
  Consists of correspondence and printed matter related to Die Grünen, the German Green Party, of which Knapp was a member.
  - Bundesvorstand correspondence and printed matter, 1980-1981 (Box-folder 15:1-16:6; 27:6-30:2)
  - General correspondence, 1978-1985 (Box-folder 16:7-18:2; 26:1-3; 54:2-7)